בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף Daf is נ"ב, Nun bet, נ"ב עמוד א', Nun bet
amud aleph, we start at the very first line at the משנה.
Mishna. We had gone through a little bit of an aside with
on the theme of things everything that is A is B but
there are things that are B that are not A, but now
we get back to the main theme which had not been נדה
Niddah per se but had been the question about the different ages
and stages of physical development and halakhically the different ages as a
young man or woman grow up. And so we are still going
to wrap that up before we finally get back to נדה Niddah
per se. So let's take a look at the משנה Mishna top
of נ"ב עמוד א'. Nun bet amud aleph. תינוקת
שהביאה שתי שערות. Tinokes she'heivi'ah shtei sa'aros. So a literally a baby
girl, but it really means a young girl, somebody who's not yet
an adult, but now she has two pubic hairs. And what's not
stated here, but we sort of know from previous discussions and previous
משניות, Mishnayos, is that she's at least 12 years and a day
and has two pubic hairs. So in that case חולצת או מתייבמת.
Chuletzes o misyabemes. She's considered an adult and as an adult one
example used classically for that is the question, you know, thank you
so much for for you know for boys if you wanted to
say an adult you know you would point out well you know
תפילין, Tefillin, ציצית, Tzitzis, can be a שליח ציבור Shliach tzibbur maybe
those types of things. For a girl interestingly the examples because so
many of those rituals even if they're not excluded from or not
whatever necessarily were not norm for the for for girls so the
classic examples for girls that are used for the question of adulthood
are issues related to marriage. Now it can't be whether they can
be married because you can be married as a girl even as
a minor if the father marries her off. So the classic example
therefore is חליצה Chalitzah or יבום. Yibbum. Only an adult man or
woman could do חליצה. Chalitzah. יבום Yibbum might be able to be
done by minors on that's a debate. But חליצה Chalitzah can only
be by adults so one example of being an adult is that
you can do חליצה. Chalitzah. Okay so that's what the משנה Mishna
says once she has two pubic hairs and is 12 years old
and a day she can do חליצה. Chalitzah. Because of consent? No
because then you would think it would certainly be required by יבום
Yibbum as well but it's because of the word in the פסוק.
Passuk. The verse says that the man and we're going to see
that in the גמרא Gemara it assumes the man is parallel to
the woman so it's just in the act of חליצה Chalitzah uses
the word man which means according to the חכמים Chachamim the an
adult man. So it's not if it were based on consensus if
anything you would think you would more need consensus for יבום Yibbum
than for חליצה Chalitzah so it's really framed just based on the
word in the verse. So once she is that she's an adult
and therefore she can do חליצה Chalitzah or יבום. Yibbum. וחייבת בכל
המצוות האמורות בתורה, Vechayaves bechol hamitzvos ha'amuros batorah, although again we're not
sort of pointing out her eligibility for certain religious you know ritual
acts which again are most more obvious by by the boy
nevertheless in terms of her obligations as a בת מצוה Bat mitzvah
girl as an adult girl she is obligated in all מצוות Mitzvos
in all positive in all negative prohibitions and all positive מצוות Mitzvos
except for except for the side ones. Well no because there's difference
between obligations and issues that relate to the ability to engage in
you know binding transactions and issues around personal status and there could
be difference. Like you're punishable by the law right how old do
you have to be to be prosecuted as an adult 18 or
something you can't buy liquor till you're 21 right so they're not
always the same in terms of your obligations and your being bound
by the law and what your rights and privileges are.
And חליצה Chalitzah and יבום Yibbum is a מצוה מן התורה Mitzvah
min hatorah though.
No no no but that's not the question of like do you
get do you get brownie points for having done it or having
transgressed it's whether it's effective if you do חליצה Chalitzah or יבום.
Yibbum. So that's a different question from your obligations. Well well
yes but we know that as if they have no if they
have no father to marry them biblically and if they have no
mother or brothers to marry them rabbinically then they can't be married
to marry themselves until they're an adult.
But but they can we've learned a three years and one.
No I said if they have no father to marry them off
or mother to marry them off they can't themselves they can't give
themselves in marriage till they're an adult right. Okay so that's in
terms of girls.
וכן תינוק Vechein tinok similarly young boys שהביא שתי שערות she'heivi shtei
sa'aros that brings has two pubic hairs and again is of the
right age חייב בכל מצוות האמורות בתורה Chayav bechol mitzvos ha'amuros batorah
is obligated interestingly here right it could have given a lot of
examples about marriage could say he could marry a you know a
woman he could engage in financial transactions. וחייב בחליצה Vechayav bechalitzah right
it could have said that he's eligible for חליצה Chalitzah right. So
it doesn't interestingly does not jumps right to חייב בכל מצוות האמורות
בתורה Chayav bechol mitzvos ha'amuros batorah can do all the מצוה Mitzva
is obligated in all the מצוות Mitzvos and in terms of the
one thing it does point out in terms of more like personal
status וראוי להיות בן סורר ומורה. Verayui lihyos ben sorer umoreh. He
can if he is a rebellious son right so the גמרא Gemara
in סנהדרין Sanhedrin says that this idea right the rebellious son who
gets brought out by the parents and if he keeps on violating
whatever could even get to the point of getting killed executed. So
on the one hand it's בנינו *benenu*, our son, so he has
to be young, and we'll see how at a certain point he
can no longer be considered a rebellious son, but on the other
hand the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* understands that it is because he's being
punished, he has to be an adult in order to be punished.
So don't think that he's punished as a child for being a
rebellious son, only once he becomes an adult. Now וראוי להיות בן
סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh, *vera'uy lihyot ben sorer umoreh* משיביא שתי
שערות shtei searot, *misheyavi shtei searot* from the time he has two
pubic hairs עד *ad* but it's limited because he still has to
be a בן *ben*, he still has to be young in a
certain respect, so עד שיקיף זקן התחתון *ad sheyakif zakan hatachton*, זקן
*zakan*, זקן *zakan*, right,
until the lower beard is surrounded, ולא העליון ve-lo ha-elyon, *velo ha'elyon*,
not the upper beard, אלא שדיברו חכמים בלשון נקייה ela she-dibru khakhamim
bi-leshon nekiyya. *ela shedibru chachamim bilshon nekiyah*, and as if you didn't
pick up the point, it says the rabbis are speaking in euphemistic
terms. Okay, so not the beard on his face, but the beard
in his pubic area until that you didn't get that, okay,
now you got it, now you got it. Okay, so until
then
it is
until that's surrounded which presumably means that it is, you know, goes
from sort of one end of the pubic area to the other.
After that point, he is not considered a בן *ben*. Why? Because
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, yes, but why? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says because he's an איש *ish* already, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says after that point he could father children. It assumes, which I
don't think is scientifically correct, right, I assume that even semen from
a young child, right, I mean once there's semen it could impregnate,
as is presumably there's no difference, right, is that true? I mean
at what stage does the semen have live sperm? I assume probably
from before a boy is a thirteen-year-old, right? What? I would assume
anyway.
Okay, so who knows? But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that he
cannot actually impregnate
until this later stage of physical development. Okay, so therefore, it says
בן *ben* is not that it means that he's not an adult,
he is an adult, he's thirteen and a day with two pubic
hairs, but בן *ben* means he cannot be he's not yet fit
to be a father. Once this is this stage of physical development
that there's pubic hair that surrounds, in that case he's fit to
be a father, fit to impregnate, and he can no longer be
a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh *ben sorer umoreh*. Okay, now
תינוקת שהביאה שתי שערות אינה יכולה למאן lema'en, *tinoket shehevi'ah shtei searot
einah yecholah lema'en*. Now
another going back to the girls, and this is interesting because this
you would think would be more juxtaposed to the חליצה halitzah *chalitzah*
and יבום yibbum? *yibbum*. So as an adult you can do חליצה
halitzah, *chalitzah* and יבום yibbum, *yibbum*, but as an adult you cannot
do מיאון miun, *mi'un*. What's מיאון miun. *mi'un*? מיאון miun. *mi'un* is
when the girl has a father, the father could marry her off
when she's underage, and that's binding, that's biblically marriage, the only way
to get out of it is by a גט get. *get* from
the husband. But if there is no father, then again this which
really this the rabbis instituted that the mother or brothers could also
marry her off, which the fact that they had to create that
institution reflects that there was a real socioeconomic need to ensure that
your daughters were married and to marry off your daughters, so they
allowed even the mother and brother to do it. But that's only
דרבנן *derabbanan*. So therefore, she can refuse the husband that her mother
and father, which is called מיאון miun. *mi'un*, mother and brothers married
her to, until she's an adult. Once she's an adult, she loses
the right of refusal.
No, they can only marry her as a minor and she has
a right to refuse as long as she's a minor.
Right, it takes for granted that they cannot...
it takes for granted that they have no power over her after
she's an adult. That's true. It takes that for granted, it doesn't
say that. You're correct. Okay. What? Now רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda
omer. עד שירבה השחור *Rabbi Yehuda omer ad sheyirbe
hashachor*. Right, it takes that for granted. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi
Yehuda* says, no, she could actually refuse, yes she's an adult by
two pubic hairs, as Rifka said the point that the father or
mother or daughters have, well the father actually is a little more
complicated, but the fact that the mother or brothers have no control
over her after an adult is taken for granted. But even if
she had been married off, she can refuse the marriage through מיאון
miun *mi'un* not only until it stops when she's an adult, she
has the right to do it until there is an abundance of
black, until the pubic area is basically filled with hair.
It seems different by the boy of יקיף *yakif*. יקיף *yakif* seems
to mean that it goes from one end to the other and
ירבה *yirbe* means that it's sort of filled, a black spot, it's
filled with pubic hair. Yeah.
The reality is she can always refuse.
No, what do you mean? Why? She's gotta get a גט get?
*get*. She has to get a גט get, *get*. Once she passes...
without a גט get. *get*.
Yeah, she can always refuse.
No, what do you mean? Why? She's got to get a גט.
get. She's got to get a גט. get. What, to pass without
a גט? get. Without a גט, get she can just say I
don't want to marry this guy and she walks away.
So if she is older, she has to marry...
She's been married off by her mother and brother, she's probably, she
might have even been living with this guy, okay, whether having sex
or not, could be based on earlier discussions, but until she becomes
an adult, that marriage is only rabbinic, and she can just say
I refuse and walk out. Right,
okay, and that's what we're talking about. Alright, let's take a look
at...
she can refuse, she cannot marry... Yes, I understand. It's missing the
point that they can't marry her. That's right, that's taken for granted.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara וכיון דתנן חייבת בכל
מצות האמורות בתורה, ve-keivan de-tnan hayyevet be-khol mitzvot ha-amurot ba-Torah,
once you say, this is Michael's question, once you say she's obligated
in all mitzvot, once she's a בת מצוה, bat mitzvah, חולצת ומתייבמת
למה לי, kholetzet u-mityabemet lama li,
why do you have to say she can do חליצה halitzah. or
יבום? yibbum. Presumably, as Michael said, if she's an adult, she's an
adult across the board. All the laws should be the same. הגמרא
Ha-Gemara says לאפוקי מדרבי יוסי. le-appuki mi-de-Rabbi Yosi.
No, this is coming to reject the position of Rabbi Yosi דאמר
איש כתוב בפרשה. de-amar ish katuv ba-parashah.
When it says about the חליצה, halitzah. this is also Rachel's question
about how do we know you have to be an adult, the
only word that indicates an adult, it says ואם לא יחפוץ האיש.
ve-im lo yakhpotz ha-ish. If the man does not want to do
יבום, yibbum, he does חליצה. halitzah So the only time this is
in דברים כה. Devarim kaf-heh. The only place where it uses a
phrase of adulthood is by the man and by doing חליצה. halitzah.
So that's the only place you need to be an adult, for
חליצה halitzah. for the man. Anything else can be done by minors.
So when it comes to... אבל אשה
בין גדולה בין קטנה, aval ishah ben gedolah ben ketannah, whether an
adult or a minor can do חליצה. halitzah, קמשמע לן, Kamashma lan,
so the משנה Mishnah is teaching you, no, we don't rule that
way. אי איכא שתי שערות אין, ei ikka shete se'arot in, if
she has two pubic hairs, she's an adult, she can do חליצה.
halitzah אי לא לא, ei lo lo, and if without that, she
cannot. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אשה כאיש. ishah ke-ish.
Yes, it only says the man, but the man and the woman
are parallel in this whole act of חליצה, chalitza and therefore, if
the man has to be an adult, the woman has to be
an adult.
Okay, but where does it say אשת המת eshet ha-met in the
פרשה?
parashah? Okay, but תני אשה, tani ishah, I
mean I hear, the גמרא Gemara sort of wasn't impressed with it.
והא תני אשה אשה ושבקו כלהון... ve-ha tani ishah ishah ve-shavko kulehon...
I don't know what to tell you.
וכיון דתנא וכן התינוק שהביא שתי שערות חייב בכל מצות האמורות בתורה.
ve-keivan de-tana ve-khen ha-tinok she-hevi shete se'arot hayyav be-khol mitzvot ha-amurot ba-Torah.
Once it says and the same law is true about a young
boy that has two pubic hairs that he's implicitly... what does it
mean to say? That he's an adult. So once you said it's
the same, why do you have to spell it out? Why
do you have to spell out, oh, he's obligated in all mitzvot?
You say it's the same as the girl. וכי תימא משום דקבעי
למתני וראוי להיות בן סורר ומורה. ve-khi tema mishum de-ka-ba'ei le-matni ve-ra'uy
lihyot ben sorer u-moreh. Maybe you want to say because you want
to then get in the discussion of בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer
u-moreh which is not just that it begins
with two pubic hairs, but it ends when the area is sort
of,
when it's surrounded.
And therefore, because you want to do that, you start by saying
obligated in all the mitzvot, because you want to build up to
בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh, discussion. That can't be that that's
your motivation. תנינא חדא זימנא tanina hada zimna because we already taught
that law of בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh, earlier, or in
a different place. We taught it in סנהדרין Sanhedrin where is the
פרק, perek, the chapter is בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u-moreh, and
the whole focus is on the laws of בן סורר ומורה, ben
sorer umoreh and there the משנה Mishnah says exactly what our משנה
Mishnah says. It says אימתי הוא בן סורר ומורה, eimatai hu ben
sorer u-moreh, when can he... what is the age that a child
can be in the category of a rebellious son? משיביא שתי שערות
ועד שיקיף זקן התחתון, mi-she-yavi shete se'arot ve-ad she-yakkif zakan ha-takhton, from
the two hairs until there is a... until the lower beard is
surrounded. ולא העליון, not the upper, אלא שדיברו חכמים בלשון נקייה. Word
for word our משנה. Mishnah. Okay, but the rabbis are speaking in
euphemism. So all you had to say here is the same applies
to a boy. You don't have to tell me חייב במצוות hayyav
be-mitzvot because that's implicit. You said the same applies. You don't have
to tell me the special law of בן סורר ומורה, I've got
another משנה Mishnah that teaches me that. Why are you being so
wordy here? So the גמרא Gemara says, you know what, אין הכי
נמי, in hakhi nami, you're right, it could have gotten away with
it without, just saying the same with a boy and ended. אלא
איידי דפריש מילי דתינוקת כמא פריש נמי מילי דתינוק. ela aidi de-perish
millei de-tinoket kama perish nami millei de-tinok. Since it is spelling out
all of the details of a girl, and let's face it, most
of the emphasis in this entire פרק, perek, let alone the מסכת,
masechet, but even when you're dealing with ages of physical development and
maturity, is about the stages of a girl, we might as well
spend a little time talking about the same somewhat of the implications
of the ages of development of a boy. Okay, and interestingly, it
doesn't even spell it out equally because as we said, it should
have said by the boy when he's an adult he can do
חליצה chalitzah and יבום. When it's a boy, he can do, you
know, he can enter into acts of transaction and so on. It's
actually pretty terse by the boy even if it could have said,
you know, didn't have to say everything it said here, but we
might as well spend a little time discussing the boy. Sort of
reminds me of that, you know, joke, I don't know, story or
whatever, right, you know, the guy has a sign out in front
of his store that says fresh fish sold here daily, right, you
know the story? And somebody says, why do you need that, why
do you have to say sold here? Like, do you think you're
giving it away for free? So he takes off the... Takes out
the word "here." It says, "Why do you have to say here?
Of course it's here, where else would it be?" Takes out the
word "here." It says, "Why do you have to say daily?" whatever,
goes up that he says, "Why do I need the whole sign?"
Okay, so anyway, so you didn't have to say anything, but you
know what, sometimes it pays to say it. Alright, anyway, that's the
basic issue about חליצה chalitzah, and בן סורר ומורה which we're not
going to discuss here because that we have a whole פרק perek
in סנהדרין Sanhedrin about. Now we go on, תינוקת שבאו, tinoket sheba'u,
now we're going to focus on the end of this משנה mishna
which is about מיאון, mi'un. about married off by brother or mother
and can refuse, maybe is even living with her husband now but
is under age, can refuse until she's an adult, and according to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, she can refuse until the whole area fills
with pubic hair. So אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi
Abbahu amar Rabbi Elazar, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu says in the name
of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
הלכה כרבי יהודה. halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. We rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda she has the right of refusal until this later stage of
development. And even though that's true, ומודה רבי יהודה שמנבעלה לאחר שהביאה
שתי שערות, umodeh Rabbi Yehuda sheminibala le'achar shehevia shtei searot,
if she had sex with her husband after the two pubic hairs
and before this period, even though it's not yet this later stage
of filled with, you know, filled with pubic hairs, but she's an
adult and she's had sex, she's had two pubic hairs, at that
stage שוב אינה יכולה למאן, shuv einah yecholah lema'en,
she can no longer do מיאון. mi'un Why not? Because what you
have here is is that they are living as husband and wife.
Now it is true that they're living in the context of a
rabbinic marriage done by the mother, but they're living together as husband
and wife. As soon as they have sex together after she becomes
an adult, two pubic hairs, then that sex is interpreted as קידושי
ביאה, kiddushei biah, as sex in the marital context and therefore that
makes them married biblically. And once it makes them married biblically, she
can no longer do מיאון.
mi'un, Wait, so before she has two hairs, then they, then she
can.
But if, but that's
not considered because
of, well, because because right, because before she has two hairs and
there's no father, she can't marry herself off and her parent, her
mother can't marry her off biblically, the only way she could be
married under age is if there's a living father who marries her
off. Okay, so if that's the case,
what's her status if someone nonetheless has sex with her?
Nothing. She's not a, she's not a בעולה, be'ulah, but there's no
status in terms of being bound to this man she had sex
with. Okay?
But until, like we said, three and a day.
If the father marries her off,
if the father,
if the father, right, but if there's no father, if right, correct,
correct, but this scenario is no father. So the mother's marriage is
rabbinic. It's not made biblical by her having sex with this man.
But if it says, if she has sex after she has two
pubic hairs, then as an adult having sex with this man in
a marital context constitutes קידושי ביאה, kiddushei biah, and therefore she can
no longer do מיאון. mi'un. So even though רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda.
allows מיאון miun until עד שיעיר בה השפול, ad sheya'ir bah hashiful,
until a later stage of development, that's assuming no sex. But if
there's been sex once she's an adult, then that's קידושי ביאה. kiddushei
biah. Now that is debatable because as we'll see in a minute,
but just to, just to anticipate what the גמרא Gemara is going
to say, you know, is it true, for,
I'll just take a step back, there's a basic question of do
we say כל הבועל על דעת קידושין ראשונים בועל. kol habo'el al
da'at kiddushin rishonim bo'el. Anybody who has sex is doing it in
the context of the nature of the first קידושין, kiddushin, which means
if the initial act of קידושין kiddushin was somehow not valid, right?
Let's say, you know, he gave her some object and ten years
later it turned out not to be a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah.
Do we say that since they have been living together for the
last ten years as husband and wife and having sex in a
marital context, that constitutes קידושי ביאה? kiddushei biah? Or do we say,
no, the whole thing was, was based on the assumption that the
first act was good? And since that wasn't good, this does not
constitute a new קידושי ביאה, kiddushei biah, it's all defined by that
original act and therefore they have not been married for the last
ten years. That's a debate. Now, that is a very important הלכה
למעשה halacha l'ma'aseh today because it deals with the question about dealing
right now with עגונה agunah cases and with a woman who cannot
get a גט. get And in some cases, the there's an
there's a way to say, well, if the first wedding, marriage wasn't
good, let's say there weren't kosher witnesses or something of that nature,
then she's not married, he doesn't need a גט. get. Well, what
do you mean, she's been living together with this man for the
last ten years and they've been having sex, why isn't that just
considered קידושי ביאה? kiddushei biah? So that would be this exactly this
question. Is the fact of sex in a marital context itself constitutes
קידושי ביאה? kiddushei biah? Or does in the end, no, it's always
going to be framed based on the binding nature of that first
act. So this is partly this question as well. You could distinguish
the cases, but at some level it's this question as well. She's
been married by her mother, that's only rabbinic marriage. She's now having
sex as an adult with this man. Do we say that this
constitutes a new act of קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah and is biblically
binding? Or do we say it remains framed by the original act
of קידושין kiddushin done by the mother and it remains constituting only
a rabbinic marriage and it does not create a new biblical marriage.
So that is the question. So the גמרא Gemara here is saying
it does
create. Wait, first, present then, your question, go ahead. Wait, wait, we
have to go in order.
Wait,
even if the man is a mature person, let's say
an
adult and it's just a small little woman,
even if the man is below twelve years?
No, no, no, this all assumes that the man is an adult.
Okay, if it's a minor, right, if it's a minor this would
not apply. Yes, you did not have the mother, brother marrying off
this young girl to a young boy. They were marrying off to
a person that was an adult, that had a פרנסה, parnassah, that
whatever the ideal was, the financial sort of impetus for this was
that the assumption was boys would provide for themselves, girls were a
burden on the family, so you had to find somebody who would
be married her so that then he she would know to be
provided for. That was the sort of the societal economic norms that
created this need for this institution. Rifka, you wanted to say something.
But you said about it that only some people agree. Right, not
everybody agrees. That's why I say common law marriage is accepted as
הלכה halacha marriage in New York even if there was never...
Right, right, right. Well, right, so first of all Rav Yehuda Herzl,
Rav Yosef Eliyahu Henkin was the strong opposing voice for of common
law marriage. He said that even if the first marriage was no
good, the fact that they've been living together and having sex constitutes
קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah regardless. Status by society. Right, exactly, regardless.
And you could also distinguish between cases of no marriage. If there's
no marriage, there was no הלכה halacha marriage, meaning we didn't have
a ceremony at all, then you could say, "Well, of course we're
assuming that we're becoming married by, you know, our living together makes
us married," whereas if there was an original ceremony, that could make
things easier because then you could say we are assuming the legal
status hinges on that original ceremony.
Now they, but I had cases where they were and the פסק
psak was that if they're, if their neighborhood, if people...
If they're recognized as a married couple... They're married. Even in a
case where there was... I know, I'm saying that it might be,
it might be harder to invalidate when there wasn't a חופה chuppah
when there wasn't, as opposed to when there was and it was
invalid. Right. Rachel, yes.
Is her consent as part of this in any way
because does she need to consent to the first act of
sex as an adult?
No, as a minor...
No, no, but sex as a minor, okay, so for the, for
the question...
Does she get to consent as an adult?
Yes, yes. So are you asking within the marital context can a
woman refuse to have sex with her husband? A girl. So yes,
yes, so that's a point that Rifka made before. There's basically the
rabbis do speak against marital rape, a man having sex with his
wife against her consent. You know, they don't constitute it as crime
and as rape, but they do say a man is not allowed
to do that.
In the case by the girl, the minor girl, they never say
a man can't have sex with his wife who's a minor because
that's implicitly, you know, not real consent anyway and so they never
say anything like that. They assume he can have sex with his
wife who's a minor and that's taken for granted in these discussions.
If the girl would actually say, "I don't want to," then presumably
that would fall into the general rule of against, that a man
shouldn't be having sex against his wife's will.
So if she has sex as a minor and she stops having
sex
as an adult before she became an adult... Then she is free
to do מיאון. miun. Then she is free to refuse.
They don't count the history.
Correct, because the only issue here is if she had sex as
an adult with this man, then as an adult that constitutes an
act of marriage. That's what, that's what is being said here. We
will see in a minute that this is debated. So let's get
a little bit, let's get past this piece where it makes a
difference. She's... No, because if we rule like, no, we rule like
Rav Yehuda that she can do מיאון miun, until יערבה השפיר, yarba
hashapir, which means that she might have six months or or a
year or whatever it is to do מיאון, miun. but she loses
that right once she once she has sex.
But if she's like, but she can't be like, she didn't have
sex for twenty years, it's still too late?
Obviously, the נפקא מינה nafka mina is from, is from two pubic
hairs until יערבה השפיר. yarba hashapir. All right, all right.
All right, wait a minute.
You mentioned something about a minor girl. Correct.
This is only if the mother, father marries her, she needs a
גט.
For twelve years old. Right, if the father marries her off, whether
to a brother or to another, he can... The husband has sex
with her, she's not gonna consent or not. Right.
Correct. And if the father married her off, then she cannot do
מיאון. miun, Correct. So what you said Rachel is only if the
mother...
Yes, yes. Okay, all right.
Or the brother.
Or the brother. Okay, all right. So moving on. Right, all right.
Yes, yes. Now let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
Father marries her off, binding marriage, biblically binding, only get out of
it with a גט. Okay, if the mother or brother marries her
off, it's rabbinic, get out of it until she becomes an adult,
according to Rav Yehuda she can get out of it even after
an adult until she has sex, her pubic hairs completely filled in,
but if she has sex as an adult... that it becomes biblically
binding is the argument, and then she can't get out of it
even according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda Now the גמרא Gemara. goes
on.
So. Okay. חברוהי דרב כהנא, Chavruhei deRav Kahana, the colleagues of רב
כהנא, Rav Kahana, סברו למיעבד עובדא כרבי יהודה, savru lema'avid uvda keRabbi
Yehuda, they wanted to rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, to allow
this girl whose mother had married her off to do מיאון miun.
even as an adult, אף על גב דניבעלה, af al gav d'nivala,
even though she had sex as an adult. So they didn't want
to limit themselves to this case. They were going to assume that
even with sex, it stays based on the context of the original
marriage and it is not a new biblically binding marriage, and she
is still entitled to do מיאון. miun. Okay, so they they wanted
to do that.
עד שירבה השחורה, Ad she'yarba ha'shachora, until until the black pubic hair
increases.
אמר להו רב כהנא, Amar lehu Rav Kahana, so רב כהנא Rav
Kahana said to them, לאו כך היה מעשה בביתו של רבי ישמעאל,
lo kach haya ma'aseh bevito shel Rabbi Yishmael, how can you how
can you say it's allowed after she's had sex? Don't you know
the story of the daughter of רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? Let's see
this story. שבאת לבית המדרש, Sheba'as leBeis HaMidrash,
so רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael had been dead. Her mother married רבי
ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael wife, this girl's mother married her off, and now
she was an adult and she came to the בית המדרש. Beis
HaMidrash. שבאת לבית המדרש, Sheba'as leBeis HaMidrash, למאן, she wanted to do
מיאון, miun, she wanted to refuse the husband that she had been
married to by her mother. ובנה מורכב על כתיפה, Uvna murchav al
ketayfa, however, she had already a child from this living with this
man. Okay, so presumably and the assumption is based as we found
earlier גמרות Gemorot that the assumption is that girls are not having
children until they are בת מצווה Bat Mitzvah as a general rule.
So the assumption is that she's had sex with this man now
as already as an adult or had her child as a result
and she still wants to do מיאון. miun She still thinks that
she can do מיאון, miun. maybe it's not עד שירבה השחורה, ad
she'yarba ha'shachora, right, it's not the second stage of רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, so she wants to do מיאון. miun, Okay, so let's take
a look what's going to happen.
What? No, it said between 11 and 12 they can get pregnant
but it's a סכנה. sakana. Less than no, that's what the daughter
of of Caesar said. The גמרא Gemara rejected that. Okay, anyway, okay,
so presumably she's had sex as an adult now, but she still
wants to do מיאון. miun ובנה מורכב על
כתיפה,
Uvna murchav
al ketayfa,
her child was on her shoulders. ואותו היום הוסקרו דבריו של רבי
ישמעאל בבית המדרש, Ve'oso hayom huskeru devarav shel Rabbi Yishmael beBeis HaMidrash,
that day the statements of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael were were quoted
in the בית המדרש. Beis HaMidrash. And we'll see that according to
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, her father's ruling, she would have been allowed
to do מיאון, miun. we will find out in a minute.
ובכתה בכייה גדולה בבית המדרש, Uvachta bechiya gedola beBeis HaMidrash, and she
and she cried or
the other גירסא, girsa, ורבצה בכייה גדולה בבית המדרש. veravtsa bechiya gedola
beBeis HaMidrash.
And there was an enormous crying, it's not just she, רבצה ravtsa
is very different than ובכתה, uvachta, it's not just she's crying, right,
everybody sort of burst out crying in the בית המדרש. Beis HaMidrash.
אמרו, Amru, and they said, not just she notice, דבר שאמר אותו
הצדיק יכשל בו זרעו, davar she'amar oso hatzadik yikashel bo zaro,
the thing that that righteous person said, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said,
will now his daughter be a stumble? Meaning he basically he ruled
in a certain way and now his daughter is going to not
you know suffer and why is she rule we haven't quoted it
yet? Let's take a look. Now from the way it sounds like
this, it sounds like his ruling is going to hurt his daughter,
make her not able to do it, but we'll see in a
second that his ruling actually would have allowed his daughter to do
מיאון miun. and the problem was was that he was overruled. So
the issue was was that the same thing that he ruled that
should have that should have helped his daughter, because the way we're
ruling now his daughter is going to be prevented from doing מיאון.
miun So let's take a look. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל משום
רבי ישמעאל, De'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi Yishmael, because רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of שמואל Shmuel in the
name of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, והיא לא נתפשה. ve'hi lo nitpasa.
This is about a woman that is married that has been that
has had committed adultery that she's forbid or I mean actually it's
a case of a סוטה, sota, correct, suspected of adultery but the
assumption is if she commits adultery then she's forbidden to her husband,
and it says because she has not been raped. So because she
has not been raped, therefore אסורה. asura. הא נתפשה, Ha nitpasa, if
a woman, a married woman, has been raped, מותרת, muteres, then even
though she's had sex with another man she's been raped, so she's
permissible to her husband. ויש לך אחרת, Ve'yesh lach acheres,
there's another woman, שאף על פי שלא נתפשה, she'af al pi she'lo
nitpasa, even though she's been married to a man and she could
have had she could have sex with another man without having been
raped, מותרת, muteres, and not made forbidden. What is that? What would
that be case? What is that case? ואיזו היא, Ve'eizo hi, what
is this? ואיזו זו שקידושיה קידושי טעות, Ve'eizo zo shekidusheha kidushei taut,
it would be a case where a woman was the initial marriage
was somehow in error. It wasn't a פרוטה, prutah, רש״י Rashi says
there was a stipulation that wasn't met. So the original marriage was
in error. שאף על פי שבנה מורכב על כתיפה, She'af al pi
she'uvna murchav al ketayfa,
even if her child is riding on her shoulders, וממאנת והולכת לה,
umema'enes ve'holeches la, she could refuse her first husband and walk away.
Now this is not the case, I know this is not the
case of מיאון, miun we're assuming the מיאון miun would be the
same הלכה, halacha, maybe because it uses the same phrase. But the
reading of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is the following: I'll give you
a case that a woman who's had sex with an a married
woman who's had sex with another man and it's not adultery even
if it's willingly.
No, no, no, well, maybe, but not necessarily. Here's the case. She's
living with a man, she's married to him, there was a whole
חופה וקידושין, chupa ve'kiddushin, whatever, she's been living with him ten years,
they have a child, she commits adultery, it's not adultery. How could
that be? It could be because we find out the first marriage
was somehow פסול psul *pasul*, invalid. There wasn't a פרוטה *prutah*, there
weren't כשר *kosher* witnesses, there was a stipulation that wasn't met. So
now she's had sex with a man that wasn't her husband, but
you know what, and she had kids with her husband, still not
adultery because the first marriage was never valid and she can walk
away from the first marriage. ממזרים *Mamzerim*? No, no, no. Because she
was never, I mean, his kids born out of marriage are not
ממזרים *mamzerim*, okay? ממזרות *Mamzerut* is only kids born as a result
of adultery or incest. So okay, so that's what Rabbi Ishmael says.
This is the position. Okay. So she wouldn't get a גט *get*.
She would not need a
גט *get*. Okay.
This is, okay, so this is the position that if the first
marriage is invalid, she can walk away even though she's been living
with the guy. Now this is in a case of טעות *taut*,
but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that the same would be true
by מיאון miun *miun*. She's been living with this guy, it's based
on a marriage that her mother or her brothers did. So if
that, since that's all in that context, as long as she can
still do מיאון miun, *miun* on that first marriage, the fact that
she's been having sex with this guy and has a child with
this guy does not make it a new binding marriage. It's all
defined by the original thing and the same way if the original
marriage was in a טעות *taut* she can walk away, if the
original marriage was based on the mother's or brothers', she can do
מיאון mi'un *miun* and walk away. So forever? Well, until maybe forever,
maybe at least until the עת השחור *et hashachor*? But the fact
that she's had sex with this guy and has a kid with
this guy does not itself prevent it. So this is the teaching
of Rabbi Ishmael. So according to Rabbi Ishmael, she should have been
able to walk away. Who cares that she's had sex and had
a kid? It's all based on the original marriage, she's doing מיאון
mi'un. *miun*, she should walk away. So but there was a problem.
What was the problem? The problem was it says ונמנו וגמרו *venimnu
vegamru*,
but they, but they, but they took a vote and they concluded
עד מתי הבת ממאנת ad masay habas memanes, *ad matai habat memanet*,
until how long can the daughter do מיאון mi'un. *miun*, עד שתביא
שתי שערות ad shetavi shtay se'arot. *ad
shetavi shtei searot*, only if, only until she has two hairs. They
basically overruled Rabbi Ishmael and they said that if she's been having
sex after she's had two hairs, then she can no longer do
מיאון miun? *miun* and she was stuck. Now I do have to
tell you that there are two ways of reading this. The way
I read it I think was a little bit the more sympathetic,
that like everybody in the בית מדרש midrash *beit midrash* was so
devastated that she couldn't do מיאון miun? *miun*, why? Because what Rabbi
Ishmael said had been overruled. But then that's a hard read of
the case because then it's not what the צדיק *tzadik* said his
daughter is stumbling on, it's because his father was overridden that היא
כשלה בו *hi kashla bo*. And it actually found, but at least
that rule, it has the בית מדרש *beit midrash* sympathetic with her.
But it sounds like perhaps the other read is, is that they
felt that for her to leave her first husband and have this
child essentially, effectively out of wedlock, and go leave this man that
she had her child with just because she doesn't like him, that
would be a type of יכשל בו זרעה *yikashel bo zar'ah*. They
didn't think that was a right choice, that for her to leave
her husband that she has a child with based on her father's
ruling, that would cause her to have made a mistake. That's their
read, and therefore ונמנו וגמרו *venimnu vegamru*, they chose in the בית
מדרש *beit midrash* to overrule Rabbi Ishmael and to prevent her from
doing חליצה *chalitza*. So I think that's probably a better read, not
better nicer, but better in terms of it fits the text more,
that they were offended that she should be using her father's ruling
and walk away with a child from this man, and therefore they
said, you know what, we're overruling your father. Yes.
I'm totally confused, if it's the father's ruling, then wasn't it her
father's marriage?
No, her father died and then she was married off by the
mother. Yes.
But
from the
late, the late father's ruling, correct.
So they're saying that this girl who hadn't yet reached puberty, her
mother married her off, she had a child, and they're continuing living
together, and you threw in a phrase 'just because she doesn't like
him' which is not in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* at all. Maybe
he was cruel?
Right, it's a, you're right, you're absolutely correct.
She didn't like him?
You're right, I did not mean to trivialize it, but you are
absolutely correct. Okay, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. Okay, I did not mean
to trivialize. I meant to say you're allowed to, and my point
of saying that, I don't even remember saying that, but my point
of saying fine, I apologize, my point of saying that was that
if she's allowed to, then she's allowed to for whatever reason under
the sun. If she's not allowed to, then she's not allowed to
even if she has the best of reasons.
But she was
desperate, really she's
crying, or they were crying, it's not clear.
Right, she's begging them to let her out of this
and they're refusing, which
is maybe very serious. Exactly, exactly. You're absolutely right. Well no, they
can give, they can allow her to have a גט *get*.
Well no, they'd have to force him to give her a גט
*get*, and that might, right. Yes.
That's how they make a comparison between a marriage
that was a טעות *taut* and this type of a marriage.
And the mother marrying off was a correct
marriage,
רבנן *rabanan*, right, this
is... A case about the original marriage being in error as opposed
to the original marriage being rabbinic and based on the mother and
brothers, but they're assuming the same because they're assuming the question is
what status do we give the act of sex that occurs in
the marital context when the original marriage was not biblically binding. So
it assumes that the same ruling for a marriage in error is
a marriage that's only rabbinically binding and if the act of sex
constitutes marriage in one case it does for the other and if
it's not in one it doesn't for the other, but it is
possible to distinguish the cases and that's what תוספות Tosafot discusses. There
are opinions that distinguish those cases. Yes David.
Are you suggesting that the second read that it was because רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael was the father that they considered it inappropriate?
No, I wasn't suggesting that. I was just saying like they felt
it would be wrong to leave this man and how could we
let her rely on a ruling of her father, meaning it's not
that they, how could we allow her to rely on a ruling
that's going to set her on the wrong path? And then you
know and how should it be that her father's פסק psak should
allow her to make a bad decision? So therefore they because they
felt it was a wrong choice they decided they took a vote
and they overruled the father. I think that's the better read of
the גמרא Gemara which makes it obviously that much more insensitive to
less responsive.
This happens all the time today in בתי דין batei din except
the only difference is this very young girl who's an עגונה. agunah.
Right, right. To have a young girl who's an עגונה agunah who's
begging to be
released because they wouldn't give her the גט and they are saying
no.
And here actually she had a ruling to support her and it
was her own father's ruling and they're saying right we actually don't
think that that's the right decision. Right. Very harsh. It's a very
good point. Okay last point and then we got to move. Yes.
I understand what we're saying. I just find it a little bit
difficult to say that you know if people living together for like
ten years in a regular marriage and then you know they're surely
thinking they're married and they say oh we're going to find some
פסול in the beginning but you know they they were still thinking
they're married for the next ten years.
Right, so it all hinges on the first thing? Yes, and what
what's that?
That's exactly the debate. So you're siding with the בית דין Beit
Din that says it's not a קידושי ראשונים kiddushei rishonim involved, but
anyway that's okay, so that's the question I
find it hard.
Okay, part of the question is how much does קידושי ביאה kiddushei
biah is it the fact of having sex in a marital context
or is it an act of a conscious act of effecting marriage
through an act of sex? And if it's the latter then you
need intention that marriage should be created through this act. It's not
just the reality. Yes for קידושין kiddushin if her father isn't marrying
her off, if she's an adult then she needs to have intention
as well. All right, let's keep on moving. All right, all right,
moving on. So the anyway so okay just a lot of side
discussions here. So there was a so anyway they wanted a rule
to allow her to do it even after an adult and even
after she's had sex and it said whoops what about this story
about רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael daughter? You see in the end the
decision was if you've had sex as an adult I'm sorry you
cannot do מיאון. miun So now the גמרא Gemara continues. So we
don't have a response but the גמרא Gemara is not yet done.
פירש ולא עבד עובדא, perash velo avad uvda, fine, they heard the
story and therefore he withdrew, he was not able to rule to
allow her to do מיאון. miun It's it's not clear that he
said you're not allowed to do מיאון but he at least was
silenced by that response and he did not allow her to do
מיאון because she had sex as an adult.
רבי יצחק ותלמידי רבי חנינא Rabbi Yitzchak v'talmidei Rabbi Chanina עבדו עובדא
כרבי יהודה ואף על גב דניבעלה. avdu uvda k'Rabbi Yehuda v'af al
gav d'niv'alah.
Again there are people willing to rule even after she's had sex
as an adult. They ruled like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda she could
still do מיאון until there was the pubic hair was filled with
hair. ואזל רב שמן בר אבא ואמר קמיה דרבי יוחנן. v'azal Rav
Sheman bar Abba v'amar kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan. So רב שמן בר אבא
Rav Sheman bar Abba went and reported this before רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. אזל רבי יוחנן ואמר קמיה דרבי יהודה נשיאה. azal Rabbi Yochanan
v'amar kamei d'Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan went and he reported it to רבי יהודה
נשיאה Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah which was the political head, it was he
was the grandson of רבי יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. שדר בולשפי
ואפקינהו. shadar bulshafi v'apkinehu.
So רבקה, Rivka, if you wanted something to respond to, he sent
troops and they took her away from her second husband. So there
was a ruling that allowed her to do מיאון after having sex
with the first husband, she did מיאון, she went and she married
a second husband and for some reason this was seen as such
a terrible ruling and such an affront that they got them to
send troops to actually take her, police, to take her away from
her second husband and put her back with her first husband.
You're not allowed to.
You're not allowed to what? You're not allowed to go back. She
was like a runaway slave in other words.
I hear the גמרא. Gemara Right. I hear the point. What? Yes.
Is she allowed to take back to her first wife if she
has...?
Well okay that's an interesting question. If she has sex with the
second man was assumed to be permissible because it was based on
a ruling then that might not make her forbidden to her first
husband. That is a whole discussion in יבמות. Yevamot. What happens if
a woman remarries assuming her husband is dead and she has reason
to assume it and it turns out her husband is alive, can
she go back? to her husband and so on. So that's a
separate discussion, but there are cases where she can. Okay. So, but
that's a very good question about how she can go back to
the first husband. It doesn't say she went back to the first
husband, just says that they took her away from the second husband.
Okay, so anyway. All right, yes. אמר רב חסדא אמר מר עוקבא,
Amar Rav Chisda Amar Mar Ukva, לא שירבה השחור ממש, Lo she'yarba
hashachor mamash, now that we're done with that very
challenging discussion about whether she can do מיאון after she's an adult,
we go back, after she's had sex, now we get to a
more technical discussion about how much pubic hair constitutes the state for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda with even with, with or without sex, she
can no longer do מיאון. So אמר רב חסדא אמר מר עוקבא,
Amar Rav Chisda Amar Mar Ukva, לא שירבה השחור ממש, lo she'yarba
hashachor mamash, it does not really mean that the place has to
be filled with hair, black has to fill the place, אלא כדי
שיהיו שתי שערות שוכבות ונראות כמי שירבה השחור על הלבן. ela kedei
sheyihiyu shtei searot shochvot venir’ot kemi sheyarba hashachor al halavan.
Even if it's two pubic hairs, but they're so long that if
you would lie them down flat, they would basically cover the entire
space. Now I don't still see how two hairs are going to
ירבה השחור. yarba hashachor. I understand that means you don't need hair
in the entire area, because if it's just if you could lie
the hair flat, it would fill the area, but I'm not sure
how that works with two hairs. Anyway, רבא אמר, Rava amar, what?
Very, very long.
I guess. רבא אמר שתי שערות המקיפות משפה לשפה. Rava amar shtei
searot hamakifot misafa lesafa.
Two hairs that surround from one edge to the next. Now again,
I'm not exactly sure how to read this. Does that mean that
the two hairs are so long that they go from one edge
of the region to the other? Then I don't see how that's
really that much different than what we just said. Maybe it means
that you have a row of hairs that go the entire region
from one edge to the next, and then when you lie them
flat, then they fill the region, but of course then why again
does he say שתי שערות, not clear to me. אמר רבי חלבו
אמר רב הונא, Amar Rabbi Chelbo Amar Rav Huna, שתי שערות שאמרו,
shtei searot she'amru, צריך שיהיה בעיקרן גומות. tzarich sheyehei be'ikaran gumot.
When they spoke of two hairs, now this might be going back
to the classic two hairs, forget this later stage for מיאון. The
normal idea that a young boy or young girl needs two pubic
hairs to be considered an adult. So what when we say those
two hairs, they have to be coming from גומות, gumot, they have
to be coming from follicles. Okay, I don't know if you can
have a hair without that coming from a follicle. So now let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. רב מלכיו אמר רב אדא בר
אהבה, Rav Malkio Amar Rav Adda Bar Ahava, גומות אף על פי
שאין שערות. gumot af al pi she'ein searot. If you have follicles
even without having hairs, that is sufficient. So I don't know, will
you have a follicle before hair grows from it? I mean, if
I'm looking at my hand, I don't know.
I think so.
So you can presumably have a follicle before hair has grown from
it.
Some say even
before hair.
So we discussed that the other day. Some say women look for
girls, but some say, what?
Not all these cases. Some of the cases we might be going
back to the case of the משנה Mishnah about whether she can
do חליצה or יבום, whether she's obligated in מצוות mitzvos and so
on. Anyway, we had that discussion before who's looking for the hairs.
All right, anyway. What? Right, she was not, she
didn't go through puberty
yet and she still got pregnant.
Well,
no,
we
would the whole assumption assumed that he had the baby after puberty,
after twelve years and a day. It just wasn't yet the stage
of ירבה השחור. yarba hashachor. Married before.
Right, married before, had the baby after puberty, right. And it just
hadn't hit the stage of ירבה השחור. yarba hashachor. No, we were
working with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that she can do it until
ירבה השחור, yarba hashachor, right. Okay, let's try to get a little
bit further here.
Okay, so he says follicles even without hairs. אמר רב חנינא בריה
דרב איקא, Amar Rav Chanina Berei DeRav Ika, שפוד שפחות וגומות רב
מלכיו, בלורית אפר מקלה וגבינה רב מלכיא. Shipud, Shfachot veGumot Rav Malkio,
Belorit, Efer Makleh veGvinah Rav Malkia.
So there were three statements said by a רב מלכיו Rav Malkio
and three statements said by a רב מלכיא, Rav Malkia, and it
was and they got a little bit confused who said what, so
they tried to list who said what. So רב מלכיו Rav Malkio
said the rulings about שפוד, shipud, about a certain type of a
spit used in, you know, whatever, not our case, שפחות shfachot about
about maidservants, also a separate discussion in כתובות, Kesubos, and גומות, gumot,
this ruling about follicles without hairs. All of that was said by
רב מלכיו. Rav Malkio. Now the case of בלורית, belorit, which is
a type of a hair cut which was done in a sort
of pagan style, so and there's a point that a Jewish barber
cannot cut that area even of a non-Jew, and there was a
question about what is the area, how is that area defined, and
there was a definition of where that area was. אפר מקלה, Efer
Makleh, which is also a question about does ashes and the use
of ashes in various types of things, and גבינה, gvinah, another question
about whether why cheese of non-Jews is not kosher, and there was
an explanation given, all of those were given by רב מלכיא. Rav
Malkia. Okay, now that we got that clear. רב פפא אמר, Rav
Papa amar, no, that's not the right list. מתניתין ומתניתא רב מלכיו.
Matnitin uMatnita Rav Malkio. Anything that's based on explaining a משנה Mishnah
or a ברייתא, Braisa, those three of those cases were about משנות
Mishnas or ברייתות, Braisas, that was רב מלכיו. Rav Malkio. שמעתתא, Shma'teta,
things that were
אמוראי Amoraic teachings, that was רב מלכיא. Rav Malkia. וסימנא, VeSimana, we'll
say it in a minute. וסימנא, VeSimana, the way to remember it
is מתניתין מלכתא, Matnitin Malchasa, that the משנה Mishnah is the queen.
is the queen. So מלכיא Malkia sounds somehow more like מלך, Melech,
I don't know, than מלכיו, Malkio, מלכיא Malkia sounds like מלכא, Malka,
I guess. So anyway, then you can remember that רב מלכיו Rav
Malkio was the one that said about משניות mishnayos and ברייתות. baraitas.
So מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? How does that shift the list? איכא
בינייהו שפחות. ika beinaihu shvachos. It shifts the list in regarding to
the במצר, be-metzer, why? Because רב מלכיא, Rav Malkia, the three cases
that are the משנה, mishnah, is the case of, where were we,
hold
on, בלורית, bloris, the haircut was a משנה mishnah about where do
you cut the hair of a non-Jew who has this haircut? And
the גבינה, gvina, the cheese was a משנה mishnah about cheese of
non-Jews being non-kosher. So in order to make the all three of
them to be משנה, mishnah, you have to take out the אפר
מקלה, eifer mikleh, which is an amoraic statement, and replace it with
the case of the שפחות, shvachos, of the maidservants, which is a
משנה mishnah in כתובות. Kesuvos. Fine. So the list is not haircut,
ashes, and גבינה, gvina, it's haircut, maidservants, and cheese. All those three
were משניות mishnayos or ברייתות baraitas and they were explained by רב
מלכיא. Rav Malkia. Moving on. אמר רב אשי אמר לי מר זוטרא,
Amar Rav Ashi amar li Mar Zutra, so מר זוטרא Mar Zutra
said to me, קשיא ביה ברבי חנינא מסורא. kashya beih be-Rebbi Chanina
mi-Sura. So רבי חנינא מסורא Rebbi Chanina mi-Sura was bothered by this
ruling that follicles were enough. לא אשתמיט תנא ואשמעינן גומא? lo ishtamit
tana ve-ashmieinan guma? How could a תנא tana never never missed this
case and teach us about the follicles? This is the question about
lack of evidence, when is lack of proof proof? So sometimes the
גמרא Gemara says look, sometimes if we talked about all of ש"ס
Shas about two hairs, and we've never said two follicles, we've always
said two hairs. I can't accept your statement that follicles count instead
of hairs. The תנא tana would never have let escape the opportunity
all those opportunities to say and one of them at least say
the idea of follicles if that were true. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, it could still be true. אשמעינן גומא, ashmieinan guma, had
the תנא tana told us about follicles, הוה אמינא hava amina עד
דאיכא שתי שערות בשתי גומות. ad de-ika shtei sa'aros bi-shtei gumos. You
need two hairs out of two follicles, you always always need two
follicles. קא משמע לן kamashma lan דאפילו שתי שערות בגומא אחת. de-afilu
shtei sa'aros be-guma achas. That two hairs count even if it's only
one follicle. I don't know if that happens or not, I don't
know. Anyway, so the argument is it could still be follicle by
itself and the reason we say hair is to include a case
of two hairs from one follicle. So that's the argument still that
there are cases it could be that follicles is good by itself.
Now the גמרא Gemara... says ומי איכא כי האי גוונא? u-mi ika
ki hai gavna? Is it really possible, the גמרא Gemara asks, that
you can have two follicles from one, two hairs from one follicle?
והכתיב אשר בשערה ישופני והרבה פצעי חנם, ve-ha ksiv asher bi-se'arah yeshufeni
ve-hirbah pitzai chinam, that God swept me away with a whirlwind and
He increased my wounds for nothing. This is איוב Iyov complaining of
his plight. ואמר רבא, ve-amar Rava, רבא Rava said, איוב בשערה חירף.
Iyov bi-se'arah chiref. איוב Iyov cursed God about the whirlwinds. He said
God is punishing me for nothing. So he's basically saying I'm being
made to suffer unjustly, which is here being framed as חירף, chiref,
as blaspheming. So he does that referring to a whirlwind. בשערה השיבו,
bi-se'arah heshivu, and he was responded by a whirlwind. As anybody knows,
the end of איוב Iyov is that God appears to איוב, Iyov,
thank you so much Chozzy, that would be, God appears to איוב
Iyov in a whirlwind. So חירף, chiref, so how what was his
blaspheming? אמר לפניו, amar lefanav, he said to God, רבונו של עולם,
Ribono shel Olam, Master of universe, שמא רוח סערה עבר לפניך? shema
ruach se'arah avar lefanekha? How is it that you're punishing me? Maybe
a whirlwind passed in front of You ונתחלף לך בין איוב לאויב?
ve-nichalef lakha bein Iyov le-oyev? You got a little confused, You saw
איוב Iyov and You thought it meant אויב, oyev, You thought I
was Your enemy. How else could You be doing this to me?
So maybe You got confused. בשערה השיבו, bi-se'arah heshibo, God responded to
him in a whirlwind. ויען ה' את איוב, vayaan Hashem es Iyov,
God responded to איוב Iyov מן הסערה, min ha-se'arah, from the whirlwind.
ויאמר אליו, vayomer elav, and He said to him. And now this
is of course the גמרא Gemara now putting words now saying what
God said. שוטה שבעולם, shoteh she-ba-olam, you idiot, הרבה נימין בראתי בראשו
של אדם. harbeh nimim barasi be-rosho shel adam. I've made many hairs
on the head of a human. ולכל נימא ונימא בראתי לה גומא
בפני עצמה. u-le-chol nima ve-nima barasi lah guma bi-fnei atzmah. Every hair
has its own follicle. שלא יהו שתים יונקות מגומא אחת. she-lo yehu
shtayim yonkos mi-guma achas. And one hair cannot come out, two hairs
cannot come out of one follicle. שאילו שתים יונקות מגומא אחת, she-imalai
shtayim yonkos mi-guma achas, had two hairs come out of one follicle,
מכחיש מאור עיניו של אדם. makhish ma'or einav shel adam. It would
somehow weaken the sight of a person. Okay, so therefore two hairs
are never going to come out of one follicle. גומא בגומא לא
נתחלף לי. guma be-guma lo nishalef li. If I ensure that every
hair comes out of its own follicle, I make sure that the
world works perfectly according to the tiniest detail and one follicle from
the other is not switched for Me, איוב באויב נתחלף לי? Iyov
be-oyev nishalef li? You think I'm going to confuse איוב Iyov for
אויב? oyev? So how dare you say that I made a mistake.
So by the way you realize that the play on words is
סערה se'arah and שער, sa'ar, hair and whirlwind. Okay, anyway so all
of that fascinating little מדרש was to say how can you say
that two hairs can come out of one follicle? גמרא says לא
קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא בגופא הא ברישא. ha be-gufa
ha be-resha. This deals with the body and the head. This was
only about the head. The head, two hairs can't come out of
one follicle. The body, maybe they can. All of this is said
to defend the idea that maybe two follicles is enough without it
having to be two hairs. All right. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל.
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel. Stayed so far, the rest is going
to be about figuring out the exact issue about the hairs. The
two hairs that they said אפילו אחת על הכף ואחת על הביצים.
afillu achat al hakaf ve'achat al habeytzim. Now we're talking obviously about
a young boy; even if they're not in the same place. Even
if one is on the כף, kaf, כף kaf literally means the
palm, but here according to רש"י Rashi it's a euphemism and it
really refers to sort of like the mound above the, you know,
above the genitals. So like the pubic area. So even if one
is there and one is below by the testicles, even if they're
not in the same location. תניא נמי הכי. Tanya nami hachi. We
taught similarly, not exactly the same, about this now by a young
girl. שתי שערות שאמרו, Shtay se'arot she'amru, when they speak about two
pubic hairs, אפילו אחת בגבה ואחת בכרסה, afillu achat begaba ve'achat bechersa,
even one on her back, literally it doesn't mean back because it
has to be in the pubic area, but רש"י Rashi says it
sort of means like sort of like right underneath, below, you know,
below the genitals and one on the stomach which means in the
pubic area. But not only that, now we're going to find something
shocking. אחת על גבי קשרי אצבעותיה של יד ואחת על גבי קשרי
אצבעותיה של רגל, Achat al gabei kishrei etzbe'oteha shel yad ve'achat al
gabei kishrei etzbe'oteha shel regel, that the statement here is that actually
hairs will also grow at the age of maturity, not just in
the pubic area but on the hands and on the feet. So
if you have hair that's growing on the hands or hair for
hands, hair that also counts. And not only that, you can combine
hair on the hands with hair on the feet. Presumably you can't
combine hair on the hands with hair on the genital area, but
at least, you know, this type of, those types of hairs you
can combine even though they're different areas. And even though they're not...
Now until now all we've known is is that facial hair for
a boy is a proof of pubic hair. But here the claim
seems to be that hair in other places of the body can
equally count for defining maturity. Or it's seen as a proof... we'll
see in a second it's spelled out. Not just seen in the
genital area, you see them on the hand? Yeah, but here it's
not as a proof, here it's seen as itself constituting hair according
to this position. דברי רבי שמעון בן יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Shimon ben
Yehuda. That's רבי שמעון בן יהודה איש כפר עכו Rabbi Shimon ben
Yehuda Ish Kefar Akko שאמר משום רבי שמעון. she'amar mishum Rabbi Shimon.
That he said this in the name of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
So that's much more than what we're used to. רבנן אמר רב
חסדא. Rabbanan amar Rav Chisda. And the rabbis say in the name
of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, עד שיהיו שתי שערות במקום אחד. ad
sheyihyu shtay se'arot bemakom echad. I'm sorry, the two hairs have to
be in the same place and also presumably they have to be
in the pubic area, not in other areas. He said even אחת
על הכף ואחת על ה. achat al hakaf ve'achat al ha. No,
no, no. They disagree with the whole thing. And they have to
be... the two have to be literally in the same location and
in the pubic area. Yes. So I don't understand why the criterion
is two hairs. Yes, because I just don't understand. First of all,
it's easy to pull out two hairs. Well the גמרא does discuss
that concern about how do we know and maybe there were the
hairs and they fell out and so on. So that was discussed
in the previous days. But wouldn't you want a little more evidence?
I mean, well if you have two hairs then that's enough evidence.
Your point is just lacking hairs is not necessarily evidence that you
haven't had them and the גמרא discussed that issue. But the גמרא
wants to define the immediate beginning stage of puberty. And you're saying
that there's a lot riding on those two hairs? Correct. And they're
not that difficult to get rid of. Oh you mean that somebody
who doesn't want to be an adult could pull them out. Yeah.
Okay, so that's a good point. I mean right, difference between a
גט and a not גט. Yeah, that's an excellent point. And the
גמרא... so the גמרא did discuss before other things which can, you
know, about like breast development and other things which would be evidence
even without the hairs and with them you could assume hairs. And,
you know, but that's a good point that, you know, maybe somebody's
intentionally manipulating it. I mean some cases would not be... you wouldn't
be able to do because of other evidence but some cases maybe
you could do. I don't know. I mean it should be something
that can be manipulated as opposed to something that can't be. Like
what? Like breast development. Right. So but, you know, they decided hair
is primary sexual characteristics as opposed to breasts which is secondary. Yes,
but the two hairs... we started to get rid of a lot.
I hear, I hear. It's a good point but I don't know
what to say. It's a good point. All right, let's at least
get a little bit further here. So תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. הממאנת,
hamema'enet, עד שתביא שתי שערות. ad she-tavi shtei sa'aros, To when can
a young girl do מיאון? Until she has two hairs. דברי רבי
מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda אומר. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we know says further, עד
שירבה שחור ad sheyirbeh shachor until the hair... the black fills up
the space. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, not that much, עד
שתקיף העטרה ad shetakif ha'atarah until the literally the crown is surrounded.
So it seems like that's somewhere between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
רבי יהודה that it's... that it sort of makes a rim around
even if it's not totally filling it up. בן שלקות אומר. Ben
Shalkot omer. Very interesting name, the son of שלקות. Shalkot. שלקות Shalkot
means like cooked vegetables. Says עד שתכלכל. ad shetechalkel. Until תכלכל, techalkel,
which is not clear what that even means, but רש"י Rashi and
תוספות both point us to another גמרא that somehow it means that
there is a big like mop of hair. Okay. Does it mean
עד שירבה שחור? ad sheyirbeh shachor? Is that a ירבש החוח? yarbesh
hachoach? Not exactly clear where that's different from ירבש החוח. yarbesh hachoach.
Okay, ואמר רבי שמעון, ve'amar Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
מצאני חנניה בן חכינאי בצידן, matzani Chananya ben Chakinai be-Tzidan, I found
חנניה בן חכינאי Chananya ben Chakinai in צידן, Tzidan, ואמר ve'amar and
he said to me, כשאתה מגיע אצל רבי עקיבא, keshe-ata magiah etzel
Rabbi Akiva, when you get back to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva because
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was a תלמיד talmid of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, אמור לו, emor lo, and say to him, עד מתי הבת
ממאנת, ask him till when a girl can do מיאון? אם יאמר
לך, im yomar lach, if he'll tell you, עד שתביא שתי שערות,
two hairs, because he presumed that רבי יהודה that that was רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's position, אמור לו, emor lo, say to your Rebbe,
say to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, והלא בן שלקות העיד בפני כולכם
ביבנה, ve-lo Ben Shlakot he'id bifnei kulchem be-Yavne, I happen to know
for a fact that בן שלקות Ben Shlakot testified in your presence,
in the presence of all the sages in יבנה, Yavne, right, remember
in יבנה Yavne they took testimony from all different types of people
to try to preserve what people remembered of תורה שבעל פה. Torah
she-be'al peh. So I happen to know for a fact that he
actually gave testimony in יבנה Yavne and you were there and he
said עד שתחלקל, ad she-techalkel, that it's until the hair spaces filled
with hair is a big mop of hair. He's giving her more
time. He's giving her more time, right. ולא אמרתם לו דבר, ve-lo
amartem lo davar, and you didn't say anything in response, so you've
implicitly agreed to him. How could you now be saying two hairs?
So כשבאתי אצל רבי עקיבא, keshe-basi etzel Rabbi Akiva, so רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says so when I came to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
אמר לי, amar li, he said I presumably said this to him,
he said back to me, כלכל זה איני יודע מהו, kalkal zeh
eini yodeiah mahu, I don't know what this כלכל kalkal is, maybe
I don't even know what the word refers to, בן שלקות איני
מכיר, Ben Shlakot eini makir, I don't know who this בן שלקות
Ben Shlakot guy is, עד מתי הבת ממאנת עד שתביא שתי שערות,
ad masay habas memanes ad she-tavi shtei sa'aros, I don't accept that
testimony, I don't agree, I don't believe it, I didn't hear it,
either I heard it I don't agree with it, whatever and going
back to the two hairs which as you point out is the
strictest ruling prevents the girl from doing מיאון as soon as she
becomes an adult. Let's just read till the next משנה Mishnah because
the next משנה Mishnah gets us back to נדה. Niddah. And this
is the end of the discussion of hairs. So שתי שערות האמורות
בפרה ובנגעים, shtei sa'aros ha-amuros be-parah u-ve-nega'im, when we talk about two
hairs now, interesting in comparisons, because we talk about two hairs elsewhere.
Two black hairs on a פרה אדומה Parah Adumah make it a
non-פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. Two white hairs in a spot by נגעים
nega'im have relevance for the הלכה halacha of צרעת. tzara'as. So whenever
they talk about hairs, whether it's two hairs by פרה אדומה, Parah
Adumah, whether it's by צרעת, tzara'as, האמור בכל מקום, ha-amur be-chol makom,
or in all places like by young boys and young girls, how
long, until now we've been talking about how many the hairs have
to be, how long or whatever where they are when it's just
two hairs, how long does the hair have to be? So it
says כדי לכוף ראשן לעיקרן. kedei lachof roshan le-ikaran. It has to
be long enough that you could bend over the head to touch
the base. So it has to be a long enough hair that
you could fold it over. דברי רבי ישמעאל, divrei Rabbi Yishmael, that's
what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer,
כדי לקרוץ בציפורן, kedei likrotz be-tziporen, in order that you could pull
it out by your fingernail, which is presumably even smaller, right, it
could be very tiny you could hold it by your fingernails and
pull it out. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, כדי שיהיו ניטלות
בזוג, kedei she-yihiyu nitalos be-zug, you can pull it out with tweezers,
which I would imagine is even smaller than the fingernail, but רש"י
Rashi seems to say that it's longer than the fingernail, maybe it's
easier to manipulate your fingernails than tweezers. הגמרא ha-Gemara says אמר רב
חסדא אמר מר עוקבא, amar Rav Chisda amar Mar Ukva, הלכה כדברי
כולם להחמיר. halacha ke-divrei kulam le-hachmir. We're strict, we don't know which
way to rule presumably and we're strict according in all ways, which
means that from the time it's the smallest size she can no
longer do מיאון and we have to be concerned she's an adult
and she cannot do חליצה, we don't know for sure she's an
adult until it is the longest size so we there's this grey
area and we're strict all ways. And with that we are done
with discussing these issues and we go back to נדה Niddah tomorrow.